Those of you who know me know how passionate I am
لأولئك الذين يعرفونني يعرفون مدى طموحي
about opening the space frontier.
لفتح حدود الفضاء
So when I had the chance to give the world's expert in gravity
لذا عندما أتيحت لي الفرصة لكي أقدم ﻷبرز خبير في العالم في موضوع الجاذبية
the experience of zero gravity, it was incredible.
تجربة اللاجاذبية، كدت لا أصدق.
And I want to tell you that story.
وأريد أن أحكي لكم تلك القصة.
I first met him through the Archon X PRIZE for Genomics.
قابلته لأول مرّ من خلال مسابقة "آركن" للجينوميات.
It's a competition we're holding, the second X PRIZE,
إنها مسابقة ننظمها، و هي جائزة "الإكس" الثانية،
for the first team to sequence 100 human genomes in 10 days.
ﻷول فريق يستطيع أن يسلسل مئة جين بشري خلال عشرة أيام.
We have something called the Genome 100 --
لدينا فريق يسمى "مئة الجينوم"،
100 individuals we're sequencing as part of that.
و هو يضم مئة شخص سوف نسلسل جيناتهم كجزء من المسابقة.
Craig Venter chairs that event.
"كريج فينتر" رئيس ذلك المشروع.
And I met Professor Hawking,
و قابلت بروفسور "هوكينج"
and he said his dream was to travel into space.
و قال لي ان حلمه أن يذهب إلى الفضاء.
And I said, "I can't take you there,
وقلت له لا أستطيع أن آخذك هناك
but I can take you into weightlessness into zero-g.
و لكنني أستطيع ان آخذك الى حال بدون وزن الى اللاجاذبية.
And he said, on the spot, "Absolutely, yes."
وفي الحال قال "بالتأكيد نعم ".
Well, the only way to experience zero-g on Earth
الطريقة الوحيدة لتجربة اللاجاذبية على كوكب الأرض
is actually with parabolic flight, weightless flight.
هي بالطيران الـمكافئ"بَرَبوْليك".الطيران بلا وزن.
You take an airplane, you fly over the top, you're weightless for 25 seconds.
تأخذ طائرة تطير فوق و تصبح بلا وزن لخمسة و عشرون ثانية،
Come back down, you weigh twice as much.
ثم تنزل مرة أخرى و يزداد وزنك بضعفين.
You do it again and again.
و تفعل ذلك مرارا و تكرارا.
You can get eight, 10 minutes of weightlessness --
ومن الممكن أن تحصل من ثمانية إلى عشرة دقائق بلا وزن -
how NASA's trained their astronauts for so long.
هذه هي الطريقة التي دربت بها وكالة "ناسا" رواد الفضاء لزمن طويل.
We set out to do this.
شرعنا في القيام بذلك.
It took us 11 years to become operational.
استغرقنا احدى عشر عام لكي نستعد للتنفيذ.
And we announced that we were going to fly Stephen Hawking.
وأعلنا أننا سنأخذ "ستيفن هوكينج" للطيران.
We had one government agency and one company aircraft operator say,
وكانت هناك وكالة حكومية و مشغل طائرة لشركة يقولون لنا
you're crazy, don't do that, you're going kill the guy.
"أنتم مجانين، لا تفعلوا هذا، سوف تقتلون الرجل".
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And he wanted to go.
وأراد هو الذهاب.
We worked hard to get all the permissions.
اشتغلنا بجهد لكي نحصل على كل الأذونات.
And six months later, we sat down at Kennedy Space Center.
بعد ستة أشهر ذهبنا الى مركز "كيندي" الفضائي.
We had a press conference,
عقدنا مؤتمرا صحفيا
we announced our intent to do one zero-g parabola,
و اعلنا على هدفنا بأن نقوم بـ"بربولا" اللاجاذبية مرة واحدة --
give him 25 seconds of zero-g.
وهكذا نؤمن له خمسة و عشرون ثانية بلا جاذبية.
And if it went really well, we might do three parabolas.
و ان مضت التجربة على ما يرام كان من الممكن ان نقوم بثلاثة "بربولات".
Well, we asked him why he wanted to go up and do this.
سألناه لماذا يريد أن يصعد في هذه الرحلة،
And what he said, for me, was very moving.
و رده أثار مشاعري جداً.
He said, "Life on Earth is at an ever-increasing risk
قال "ان الحياة في الأرض في خطر متزايد
of being wiped out by disaster ...
مهددة بالمحو بفعل الكوارث...
I think the human race doesn't have a future if it doesn't go into space.
أظن أن ليس للبشرية مستقبل إن لم تذهب الى الفضاء.
I therefore want to encourage public interest in space."
لذلك أريد أن أشجع إهتمام العامة بالفضاء".
We took him out to the Kennedy Space Center,
أخذناه الى مركز "كيندي" الفضائي،
up inside the NASA vehicle, into the back of the zero-g airplane.
داخل مركبة "ناسا" الى الجزء الخلفي من طائرة اللاجاذبية.
We had about 20 people who made donations --
كان لدينا حوالي عشرون شخص تبرع --
we raised $150,000 in donations for children's charities --
حصلنا منهم على مئة و خمسون ألف دولار من التبرعات لجمعيات خيرية للأطفال --
who flew with us.
وقد طاروا معنا.
A few TEDsters here.
و منهم من يحضر مؤتمر "تيد" معنا هنا.
We set up a whole ER.
وجهزنا غرفة طوارئ كاملة
We had four emergency room doctors and two nurses on board the airplane.
و كان لدينا أربعة أطباء طوارئ و ممرضتان على الطائرة.
We were monitoring his PO2 of his blood, his heart rate, his blood pressure.
و كنا نراقب كمية الأوكسجين في دمه و معدل ضربات قلبه و ضغط دمه.
We had everything all set in case of an emergency;
وكان كل شيئ جاهز في حالة الطوارئ.
God knows, you don't want to hurt this world-renowned expert.
والله يعلم انك لا تريد ان تؤذي هذا الخبير العالمي.
We took off from the shuttle landing facility,
اقلعنا من منشأة هبوط المكوك
where the shuttle takes off and lands.
حيث يقلع و يهبط المكوك.
And my partner Byron Lichtenberg and I
زميلي "بيرون ليشتينبيرج" و أنا
carefully suspended him into zero-g.
وضعناه بحرصٍ شديد في حالة اللاجاذبية.
Once he was there, [we] let him go
و عندما كان في تلك الحالة ، تركناه
to experience what weightlessness was truly like.
لكي يجرب حقيقة اللاجذبية.
And after that first parabola, you know,
و بعد تلك الرحلة الـ"بربولية" الأولى
the doc said everything is great. He was smiling, and we said go.
فال الأطباء ان صحته جيدة وكان هو مبتسم فقلنا لنذهب مرة أخرى.
So we did a second parabola.
و قمنا بـ"برابولية" ثانية.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And a third.
و ثالثة
We actually floated an apple in homage to Sir Isaac Newton
والآن أطلقنا تفاحة تحية لسير "إسحاق نيوتن"
because Professor Hawking holds the same chair at Cambridge
لأن بروفيسور "هوكينج" يرأس نفس القسم في "كيمبردج"
that Isaac Newton did.
الذي ترأسه "إسحاق نيوتن".
And we did a fourth, and a fifth and a sixth.
قمنا برحلة رابعة و خامسة و سادسة.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And a seventh and an eighth.
و سابعة و ثامنة.
And this man does not look like a 65-year-old wheelchair-bound man.
و هذا الرجل لا يبدو كرجل معاق عمره خمسة و ستون عاما.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He was so happy.
كان سعيداًً جداً.
We are living on a precious jewel,
نحن نعيش على جوهرة ثمينة
and it's during our lifetime that we're moving off this planet.
وفي خلال حياتنا سننتقل من هذا الكوكب.
Please join us in this epic adventure.
رجاءً انضموا إلينا في هذه المغامرة الملحمية .
Thank you so much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)